<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-07T14:40:36+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pal(a)eoScientometrics</title><subtitle>A team collecting data behind paleontological research</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Lavenir nou koray</title><link href="/languages/2021/02/21/lavenir-nu-koray.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lavenir nou koray" /><published>2021-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/languages/2021/02/21/lavenir-nu-koray</id><content type="html" xml:base="/languages/2021/02/21/lavenir-nu-koray.html"><![CDATA[<p>Bann koray pe soufer atraver lemond akoz resofman klimatik, parey kouma bann koray dan nou lagon morisien. Koray finn existe pandan lontan. Zo’nn evolie milyon banane desela ek zot temwin plizier epizod klimatik. Boukou finn mor ek zo’nn disparet, me ena ousi sertin ki finn sirviv sa bann epizod-la. Zeolozi donn nou loportinite pou aprann ki bann koray ki for ek ki bann koray ki vilnerab. Bann paleontolog kolekte bann koray fosil, savedir, bann koray ansien ki finn prezerve kouma ros, atraver lemond. Avek sa bann done depi bann fosil, mo analiz reaksion bann koray avek sa bann diferan epizod klimatik-la. Sa pou ed nou konpran kouma koray pou reazir dan lefitir ek kouma lavenir nou lagon pou resanble.</p>

<p><em>Corals are suffering worldwide because of climate change, just like those in our Mauritian lagoon. Corals have existed for a long time. They evolved millions of years ago and have witnessed several episodes of climate change. Many died and went extinct while others were resilient enough to survive these episodes.  Geology provides us with the opportunity to learn more about what makes a coral resilient or vulnerable. Fossil corals, that is, the preserved remains of these ancient corals that have turned into rocks, are collected worldwide and studied by palaeontologists. Through the data from these fossils, I analyse the response of corals to different climatic episodes. This will help us understand how corals may respond in the future and what the future of our lagoons looks like.</em></p>

<p>Many thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/anshicat/">@anshicat</a> for the help correcting the creole version.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="languages" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bann koray pe soufer atraver lemond akoz resofman klimatik, parey kouma bann koray dan nou lagon morisien. Koray finn existe pandan lontan. Zo’nn evolie milyon banane desela ek zot temwin plizier epizod klimatik. Boukou finn mor ek zo’nn disparet, me ena ousi sertin ki finn sirviv sa bann epizod-la. Zeolozi donn nou loportinite pou aprann ki bann koray ki for ek ki bann koray ki vilnerab. Bann paleontolog kolekte bann koray fosil, savedir, bann koray ansien ki finn prezerve kouma ros, atraver lemond. Avek sa bann done depi bann fosil, mo analiz reaksion bann koray avek sa bann diferan epizod klimatik-la. Sa pou ed nou konpran kouma koray pou reazir dan lefitir ek kouma lavenir nou lagon pou resanble. Corals are suffering worldwide because of climate change, just like those in our Mauritian lagoon. Corals have existed for a long time. They evolved millions of years ago and have witnessed several episodes of climate change. Many died and went extinct while others were resilient enough to survive these episodes. Geology provides us with the opportunity to learn more about what makes a coral resilient or vulnerable. Fossil corals, that is, the preserved remains of these ancient corals that have turned into rocks, are collected worldwide and studied by palaeontologists. Through the data from these fossils, I analyse the response of corals to different climatic episodes. This will help us understand how corals may respond in the future and what the future of our lagoons looks like. Many thanks to @anshicat for the help correcting the creole version.]]></summary></entry></feed>